Finding Aid for School of Social Work (University of Michigan) Records 1935-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Social Work (University of Michigan) records
1935-2010
University of Michigan. School of Social Work.
Records of the School of Social Work (formerly the Institute of Social Work) include minutes, correspondence, curriculum records, and topical files, concerning the activities of the University's social work program under the direction of Robert Kelso, Arthur Dunham, Federle Fauri, Phillip Fellin, Harold R. Johnson, and Paula Allen-Meares.
87315 Bimu C281 2
36 linear feet
2.35 GB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred in several accessions beginning in 1972 (Donor 5182 ).
The records are open for research with the exception of personnel-related files including search, review, promotion, and tenure files which are restricted for thirty years from date of creation and student educational records which are restricted for seventy-five years from date of creation.
The University of Michigan School of Social Work record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 29
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 29
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 30-35
The first curriculum in social work at the University of Michigan was established in 1921. Staff members in sociology developed a curriculum which included background courses in the social sciences and field work. The social work program was legitimized by admission into the Association of Schools of Professional Social Work in 1925. In 1927 the regents of the university authorized a certificate in social work to be awarded to students who completed a year of work experience in addition to the undergraduate degree requirements.
In response to the demands of the Great Depression and the recommendations of a committee of prominent Detroit citizens and social work educators, the university moved to reorganize its social work curriculum. In 1935, with financial support from the Horace H. and Mary A. Rackham Fund and the McGregor Fund, the University of Michigan Institute of Health and Social Sciences was established, and was later renamed the Institute of Public and Social Administration. The institute was located in Detroit, and Robert W. Kelso, who had worked briefly at the Federal Emergency Relief Administration, was appointed as its director.
By 1945, faculty members were urging the restructuring of the Institute of Public and Social Administration and the formation of an Institute of Social Work. In order to explore the possibilities, a committee composed of faculty members from Ann Arbor was created to work with Kelso. As a result of their work, the institute remained in Detroit and designed a curriculum to enlarge the technical side of training for work in the general field of social and public welfare. It became the Institute of Social Work and included courses in social case work, group work, community organization, public welfare, research and statistics, administration, and field work.
In 1950, upon Kelso's retirement, Arthur Dunham served as the institute's acting director. That same year, the University of Michigan and Wayne State University considered merging their social work programs, or expanding one of the programs to handle all graduate education in social work in the Detroit area. After months of negotiation, Wayne State announced plans to strengthen its programs in Detroit, and the University of Michigan to reorganize its social work curriculum. The Institute of Social Work was reconstituted as the School of Social Work under the administrative direction of a dean, and the supervision of a governing faculty of the school. On March 1, 1951, the School of Social Work became the 15th school of the University of Michigan, and operations were transferred from Detroit to Ann Arbor. Fedele F. Fauri was named dean and professor of public welfare administration. He had served as director of the Michigan Department of Social Welfare, and as senior specialist in social welfare and social security of the Legislative Reference Service in Washington, D.C.
During the 1950s, the school expanded its curriculum, hired new faculty members, and strengthened its intra-university ties to the social sciences. The curriculum was enlarged to include courses in psychiatric social work, medical social work, and child welfare. Extension programs were also established in Detroit and throughout the state. Several important faculty members joined the school. Plans for the development of a specialization in group work were enhanced by the appointment of Robert Vinter in 1954. His teaching, research, and writing brought national attention to the school for leadership in education in the practice of social group work. Wilbur J. Cohen joined the faculty in 1956. Cohen had been director of Research and Statistics, Social Security Administration, U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. He came to the school after twenty-one years of federal service. Intra-university connections were improved in 1953 when an interdisciplinary faculty seminar on the research basis of welfare practice was begun. It was funded by the Russell Sage Foundation and headed by David G. French. The seminar resulted in the creation of a Coordinating Committee on Social Welfare Research chaired by sociology Professor Amos Hawley. This committee developed plans for a program of advanced training and research in social work and the social sciences leading to the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in social work.
In the 1960s, social work faculty members served in numerous positions of leadership in shaping national and state social welfare policies. Professor Wilbur Cohen was appointed by President John F. Kennedy as chairman of the Task Force on Health and Social Security, and as assistant secretary for legislation of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. Under President Lyndon B. Johnson, Cohen was appointed secretary of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. Dean Fedele Fauri served as a member of the Ad Hoc Committee on Public Welfare of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, and was elected president of the American Public Welfare Association in 1966. Robert Vinter worked on the State of Michigan Governor's Task Force on Juvenile Delinquency, and as consultant to President Johnson's Committee on Juvenile Delinquency and Youth Crime.
Curriculum changes, re-accreditation, and expanded enrollment occupied the school in the 1960s. The curriculum was broadened to meet the new demands of the decade and included more emphasis on course work rather than field work. The accreditation review spurred greater faculty-student interaction, as student representatives met with various task forces and served as members of the Curriculum Committee. In 1965 students formed the Student Union, which formalized student participation in school decision-making processes, and granted students seats on several school committees. An emphasis on recruitment of minorities resulted in a higher number of minority students and led to the formation of the Association of Black Social Work Students and of the Hispanic student organization, Trabajadores de la Raza. Due to an increase in financial aid opportunities through grants and scholarships, the school experienced a subsequent increase in enrollment. By 1968, the school ranked first among the seventy-five accredited schools of social work in the United States in enrollment, number of full-time students, and the number of M.S.W. degrees granted each year.
In July 1971, Dean Fauri was appointed Vice President for State Relations and Planning at the university, and Associate Dean Vinter served as acting dean. In September 1971, the Regents appointed Phillip Fellin as dean and Richard English and Shiela Feld as assistant deans. The school's governing faculty continued to provide for a Faculty Council, which served in an advisory capacity to the dean on school affairs.
In 1973, the school's ten year re-accreditation review prompted a renewed emphasis on minority recruitment and an assessment of the minority-relevant content of course offerings at the school. The School of Social Work led the university in minority enrollment, as it had done for some time, and reached 21 percent minority enrollment in 1976. Over 68 percent of the student body was comprised of women. In 1976 it was one of only seven schools to receive over 1,000 applications for its master's program, ranking second only to Columbia University. Another outcome of the re-accreditation review was the development of closer ties to other university departments, and to state and local social agencies.
On July 1, 1981, Harold R. Johnson was appointed dean following the retirement of Phillip Fellin. Prior to becoming dean, Johnson had served as director of the Institute of Gerontology from 1974 to 1981. Johnson's appointment marked a change in leadership and direction of the school. Greater prominence and support were given to teaching and research, and service activities were de-emphasized. At a time when schools of social work around the country faced diminishing resources and were being pressed to provide professional social workers with greater skills, the school embarked on a curriculum overhaul. The curriculum was completely revised to provide students with multiple practice skills, expertise in a field of service, and the capacity to assess and evaluate professional practice. The extent of the curriculum revision was expressed in the words of the Council of Social Work Education in its 1983 re-accreditation report. The report called the reforms a "courageous major revision of a well-established curriculum to conform to the reality of social practice knowledge and skills which graduates will be called upon to possess if they are to meet the needs of the profession in the changing world around us."
During Johnson's tenure as dean, from 1981 to 1993, the school continued to promote cultural and ethnic diversity. Those goals continued under Johnson's successor, Paula Allen-Meares who became dean in 1993. Major fundraising initiatives helped to focus research on poverty, racial inequalities, children and families, and also allowed the school to move forward on plans for a new building. In 1995 ground was broken for the new School of Social Work Building, designed by Sims-Varner Associates of Detroit. It was intended to foster a sense of community, with pods of faculty offices arranged around open stairways and the glass walls of its state-of-the-art library open to the lobby, lounge and corridors above. The building was officially dedicated on September 25, 1998.
Further information on the school and its programs can be found at the following URL: http://www.ssw.umich.edu/
Directors and Deans of the School of Social Work
1935-1950 Robert W. Kelso (Director)
1950-1951 Arthur Dunham (Acting Director)
1951-1970 Fedele A. Fauri
1970-1971 Robert Vinter (Acting Dean)
1971-1981 Phillip Fellin
1981-1993 Harold R. Johnson
1993- Paula Allen-Meares
The records document the founding and development of the School of Social Work from its inception as the Institute of Health and Social Sciences (later renamed as Institute of Public and Social Administration) in 1935, to its subsequent reorganization as the School of Social Work in 1951. The proposed merger with Wayne State University in 1950 is also well documented. The strength of this record group consists of 59 years of minutes (1935-1994), which include proceedings from executive, faculty, and curriculum committees.
Summary Contents List
Correspondence Correspondence, 1958-1986 (box 5)
Curriculum Course Statements, 1967-1994 (box 19-21, 30-31)
Dean's Files, 1947-1987 (box 32)
Faculty Committee on the Presidency, 1978-1979 (box 29)
Graduate and Doctoral Program, 1948-1989 (box 21-22)
Group Work Program, 1946-1970 (boxes 11-12)
Minority and Student Multicultural Affairs, 1960-1994, (box 23-25).
Minutes Curriculum Committee, 1950-1991 (box 1, 8, 13-16, 34) Doctoral Committee (box 8, 21-22 Executive Committee, 1945-1994 (box 1, 17, 29, 35) Faculty Committee (box 2-4) Faculty Council, 1969-1983 (box 4, 8, 17) Governing Faculty, 1974-1993 (box 4, 18, 36)
Personnel Personnel Files, 1954-1968 (box 28)
Student Placement and Statistics Student Placement and Statistics, 1935-1998 (box 24)
Topical Files 1935-1996 (box 25-26) 1939-1992 (box 9-10) 1950-1984 (box 6-7) 1983-2000 (box 36-37)
Winkelman and Fauri Lecture Series, 1965-1996, (box 27) Leon and Josephine Winkelman Memorial Lecture Series (aging and gerontology) The Fedele F. and Iris M. Fauri Memorial Lecture on Child Welfare
School Website Accession (on CD)
Subjects:
Dunham, Arthur, 1893-; Fauri, Federle Frederick, 1909-1981.; Fellin, Phillip.; Johnson, Harold R.; Kelso, Robert William, 1880-; University of Michigan. Center for the Study of Youth Policy.; University of Michigan. Institute of Social Work.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; Social service--Michigan.; Allen-Meares, Paula, 1948-; Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Social group work.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Fedele F. Fauri memorial lecture series in child welfare.; Leon and Josephine Winkelman lecture.
Subjects - Visual Material
West Physics Building (University of Michigan); School of Public Health Building (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan. Program in Public Health Nursing.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
Genre/Form:
College publications.
- Committee Files and Minutes, 1935-1994
  The Committee Files and Minutes, 1935-1994, are arranged alphabetically by committee name. Administrative/Executive Committee minutes are extant for the years 1957-1968. They address issues of student performance and evaluation, and as such are restricted for a period of 75 years from the date of creation. Continuing Education and Extension Committee was one of several small committees established in the mid-1970s to revise and restructure the social work curriculum. Coordinating Committee minutes, 1953-1960, deal with the funding, budget approval, and coordination of an interdisciplinary Ph.D. program in social work and social sciences. Curriculum Committee, 1951-1957 and 1970-1980, address personnel decisions, structural reorganization, and program revision. Executive Committee minutes and supporting material from the years 1945-1987 document major administrative and policy issues facing the school including the proposed merger/reorganization talks between Wayne State University and the University of Michigan social work programs. Faculty Advisory Committee minutes are available for the years 1968-1969, and document efforts to incorporate student involvement in departmental decisions and facilitate better student and faculty relations.
  Faculty Committee minutes are the most abundant in the series and cover the years 1935-1974. They are indexed, although indexes for the later years are somewhat less thorough than those of the earlier years. Topics such as enrollment, admissions, curriculum, and budgets are discussed. Faculty Council minutes, 1969-1983, primarily focus on grading practices and faculty awards and promotions. Faculty Search Committee minutes, 1971-1981, concern efforts to fill various faculty positions within the School. They are restricted for 30 years from the date of creation. Governance Review Committee minutes, 1969-1973, and Governing Faculty Committee minutes, 1974-1991, document efforts to adopt departmental regulations and establish admission criteria and course descriptions. The Governance Review Committee served in an advisory capacity to the dean, whereas the Governing Faculty Committee served the broader faculty.
  - Academic Aids Committee
    - Minutes and Memoranda, 1966-1968 (Box 13)
  - Administration and Policy Committee
    - Memoranda, 1965-1973 (Box 13)
    - Minutes, 1964-1974 (Box 13)
    - Proposals and Reports, 1963-1971 (Box 13)
  - Administrative/Executive Committee, 1957-1968 (Box 29)
    [SR RESTRICTED for 75 years form date of creation.]
  - Admissions, Financial Aid and Student Services Committee, 1963-1989; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Committee on Long Range Planning, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Community Organization, Administration, Policy, and Evaluation (CAPE) Division Committee (Box 8)
    - 1974-1981
    - Memoranda, 1977-1981; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 13)
  - Continuing Education and Extension Committee
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1973, 1976-1982 (Box 8)
    - Minutes, 1971-1978 (Box 13)
    - Supporting Materials, 1968-1978 (Box 13)
  - Coordinating Committee on Social Welfare Research, 1955-1960 (Box 1)
    (minutes and supporting documentation)
  - Credit Hour Task Force
    - Supporting Materials, 1971-1977 (Box 13)
  - Curriculum Committee
    - 1950-1957, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1988, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - 1986-1987, 7 folders (Box 34)
      (includes agendas and associated materials
      [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2023 ]
    - 1987-1988 (Box 34)
    - 1988-1989, 2 volumes (Box 34)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 34)
    - 1990-1991
  - Curriculum Renewal Committee on Student Course Evaluations, 1967-1971 (Box 13)
    - Minutes
      - 1963-1965 (Box 13)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 13)
      - 1967 (Box 13)
      - 1968 (Box 13)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 13)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 13)
      - 1974-1977 (Box 13)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 13)
      - 1980-1983 (Box 13)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 13)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 13)
    - Minutes
      - 1963-1965 (Box 13)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 13)
      - 1967 (Box 13)
      - 1968 (Box 13)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 13)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 13)
      - 1974-1977 (Box 13)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 13)
      - 1980-1983 (Box 13)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 13)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 13)
    - Minutes
      - 1963-1965 (Box 13)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 13)
      - 1967 (Box 13)
      - 1968 (Box 13)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 13)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 13)
      - 1974-1977 (Box 13)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 13)
      - 1980-1983 (Box 13)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 13)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 13)
    - Practice Skill Instruction (PSI)
      - Exemption Policies, 1973-1976 (Box 13)
      - General, 1971-1975 (Box 13)
      - Grading Policies, 1972-1974 (Box 13)
    - Reports
      - 1966-1967 (Box 14)
      - 1968 (Box 14)
      - 1969-1972 (Box 14)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 14)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 14)
      - 1982-1991, undated (Box 14)
    - Seabury, Brett-Chairman's Files, 1993-1994 (Box 14)
    - Supporting Materials
      - 1962-1965 (Box 14)
      - 1966 (Box 14)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 14)
      - 1967 (Box 14)
      - 1968 (Box 15)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 15)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 15)
      - 1972 (Box 15)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 15)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 15)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 15)
      - 1976 (Box 15)
      - 1977 (Box 16)
      - 1978 (Box 16)
      - 1979 (Box 16)
      - 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - 1982 (Box 16)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 16)
      - 1991 (Box 16)
  - Doctoral Committee, 1970-1989; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Executive Committee
    - Executive Committee, 1945-1951; 5 folders (Box 1)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 17)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 17)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 17)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 17)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 35)
      (includes supporting material)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 35)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 35)
    - 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - 1992-1993, 1 folders (Box 35)
    - 1993-1994, 1 folders (Box 35)
  - External Review Committee, 1980 (Box 17)
  - Faculty Committee
    - Indexes
      - 1935-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1954-1960 (Box 2)
      - 1960-1974 (Box 2)
    - Minutes
      - 1935-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1944-1948 (Box 2)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 2)
      - 1951-1953 (Box 3)
      - 1953-1955 (Box 3)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 3)
      - 1957-1960 (Box 3)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 3)
      - 1966-1974 (Box 4)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Faculty Council
    - 1969-1974 (Box 4)
    - 1975-1980 (Box 4)
    - 1978-1983, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Elections, 1971-1981 (Box 17)
    - Memoranda
      - 1967-1973 (Box 17)
      - 1974-1979, undated (Box 17)
    - Minutes
      - 1970-1974 (Box 17)
      - 1975-1979 (Box 17)
    - Policies, 1972-1979; undated (Box 17)
  - Faculty Council Committee Evaluation Planning Task Force
    - Memoranda, 1975-1977 (Box 17)
    - Reports, 1976 (Box 17)
  - Faculty Retreat Committee
    - Minutes, 1993 (Box 17)
  - Faculty Search Committee
    - Faculty Search Committee, 1971-1981; 8 folders (Box 29)
      [PR RESTRICTED for 30 years from date of creation.]
    - Faculty Search Committee, 1972-1975 (Box 17)
  - Governance Review Committee, 1969-1973 (Box 4)
  - Governing Faculty Committee, 1974-1980
    - 1974-1980 (Box 4)
    - Memoranda, 1975-1991; undated (Box 18)
    - Minutes
      - 1967-1976 (Box 18)
      - 1977-1979 (Box 18)
      - 1980-1985 (Box 18)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 18)
      - 1988-1991 (Box 18)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 36)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 36)
    - 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 36)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 36)
  - Field of Service Task Force Committee
    - Memoranda, 1982 (Box 18)
    - Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 18)
  - Human Behavior and Social Environment Committee
    - 1972-1982 (Box 9)
    - Memoranda, 1968-1982 (Box 18)
    - Minutes, 1972-1982 (Box 18)
  - Human Subjects Review Committee, 1981-1989 (Box 9)
  - Interpersonal Practice (IP) Division
    - 1974-1982 (Box 9)
    - Concentration Summaries, 1976-1979 (Box 18)
    - Memoranda
      - 1974-1977 (Box 18)
      - 1978-1982 (Box 18)
    - Minutes, 1974-1982 (Box 18)
    - Reports/Proposals, 1976-1982 (Box 18)
  - Interpersonal Practice Division Sub-Committees
    - "Curriculum Unit Committee"
      - Minutes, 1974-1977 (Box 18)
      - Supporting Materials (Box 18)
    - "Knowledge Development Unit,", 1974-1976 (Box 18)
    - "Miscellaneous Task Forces,", 1979 (Box 18)
    - "Student Careers Unit,", 1974-1975 (Box 18)
    - "Task Force One,", 1972-1972 (Box 18)
  - Minorities Opportunities Committee, 1974-1986; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Professional Practicum Advisory Committee, 1989-1991 (Box 36)
  - Social Welfare Policy and Service Committee
    - 1971-1982 (Box 9)
    - Memoranda
      - 1968-1973 (Box 18)
      - 1973-1980 (Box 18)
    - Minutes, 1972-1981 (Box 18)
    - Reports, 1973-1981 (Box 18)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - Visiting Committee
    - Minutes and Memoranda, 1991-1994 (Box 18)
    - Reports and Supporting Materials, 1991-1994 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Minutes, 1972; 1979 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1958-1986
  The series Correspondence, 1958-1986 (1 linear foot) is primarily comprised of files containing incoming and outgoing letters and memos from the dean's office. The correspondence was filed by name of organization or individual, and that order has been retained in the collection. It consists mainly of university correspondence; there are only five folders of correspondence to non-university individuals and organizations. University correspondence includes materials from Presidents Hatcher, Fleming and Shapiro, and from various administrators in the Vice-President for Academic Affairs office. The correspondence from the Academic Affairs office is arranged by name of each administrator.
  - University
    - Advisor to the Executive Officers (William Haber), 1970-1976 (Box 5)
    - Dean's Files
      - Dean Phillip Fellin, 1971-1972; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - School of Public Health, 1951-1974 (Box 5)
    - Departmental Memoranda, 1974-1978; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - University Presidents
      - Robben W. Fleming, 1967-1978 (Box 5)
      - Harlan Hatcher, 1958-1967 (Box 5)